<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A proclamation to redresse the mis-imployment of lands, goods, and other things giuen for charitable vses.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B12728</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99892776</idno>
  <idno type="VID">187151</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240924808</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">STC 8375</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide 506.h.10[55]</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99892776</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99892776e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B12728)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 187151)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; C7:1[55])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A proclamation to redresse the mis-imployment of lands, goods, and other things giuen for charitable vses.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
                  <author>James I, King of England, 1566-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>2 sheets (versos blank).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Robert Barker, printer to the Kings most excellent Maiestie.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1605.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Dated at end: Rockingham the xi. of August 1605. in the third yeere of his Maiesties reigne ... .</note>
                  <note>Especially directed to educational and religious foundations. Cf. STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Charities --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Charity laws and legislation --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:187151:1"/>
            <head>❧ By the King.</head>
            <head>❧ A Proclamation to redresse the mis-imployment of Lands, Goods, and other things giuen for Charitable vses.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas Lands, Tenements, Hereditaments, goods,</hi> Chattels, Money, and other things haue bene heretofore giuen, limitted, appointed and assigned, aswell by his Maiesties most noble Progenitors, as by sundry other well disposed persons; Some for reliefe of aged, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent, and poore people, some for maintenance of sicke and maymed Souldiers and Mariners, Schooles of learning, free Schooles, and Schollers in Vniuersities; Some for repaire of Bridges, Ports, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, Cause-wayes, Churches, Seabanks, and High-wayes; Some for education and preferment of Orphanes; Some for or towards reliefe, stocke, or maintenance for houses of Correction; Some for marriages of poore Maydes; Some for supportation, ayde, and helpe of yong Tradesmen, Handicrafts men, and persons decayed; And others for reliefe, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of Prisoners, or Captiues, and for ayde or ease of any poore Inhabitants, concerning pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Fifteenes, setting out of Souldiers, and other Taxes: Which Lands, Tenements, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditaments, Goods, Chattels, Money, and other things neuerthelesse haue not bene imployed according to the charitable intent of the Giuers and Founders thereof, by reason of frauds, breaches of trust, and negligences in those, that should pay, deliuer, and employ the same. For redresse and reformation whereof, remedy and reliefe haue bene prouided, in and by one Art of Parliament, made in the three and fourtieth yeere of the raigne of the late Queene of famous memory, <hi>Elizabeth</hi> late Queene of England. By the due execution of which Act, in diuers and many parts of this Realme, much good hath ensued, by the diligence and traueile of diuers of our charitable and well affected Subiects, by restoring, and true employing of diuers and many of the saide Gifts and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments, according to the true Iustitution, Ordinance, and Intention of the Founders and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors in that behalfe: And much more good his Maiestie dayly expecteth should be done in so Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a case, acceptable to God and all good men.</p>
            <p>And whereas such as haue the care, charge and gouernement of the Colledges, Halles, and hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of learning within either of the Vniuersities of Cambridge or Oxford, or of the Colleges of West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster, Eaton, or Winchester, or of any Cathedrall or Collegiate Church, were presumed by the makers of the said Act, in respect of their Professions and Offices (which ought to put them in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall memorie of their duties) to neede to Law to enforce them to the performance of so iust and charitable a worke, And therefore did by speciall Prouiso except and exempt them out of the saide Acte: His most excellent Maiestie, in his godly meditations, calling to his blessed remembrance, how good and necessarie it is, That the deuout, godly, and charitable intents of the said Founders and Giuers should be exactly and duely performed, And nothing doubting, but that the saide per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, bodies Politique and Corporate so excepted, will aswell in discharge of their owne conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (albeit they be not bound by the saide Acte) as for example to all others (that may bee enforced thereby) will speedily, Christianly, and exactly perfourme their said dutie: Yet lest that any in so
<pb facs="tcp:187151:2"/>great a number should bee found eyther so remisse, as to neglect the speedie employment of the same, or so vncharitable and vnconscionable, as in any sort, by fraude or deuices to seeke to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert or ouerthrow the true institution &amp; meaning of the said Founders or Giuers; His most excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Maiestie, in his Princely &amp; Royall care, That the said good and godly vses &amp; intents may be duely &amp; speedily employed, as is abouesaid, And that no person or persons, bodies Politique or Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate (presuming to passe away with impunity) neglect, or not performe their duties in that behalfe, Doeth (by Aduise of his Priuie Councell) straightly charge and commaund aswell all and singuler person and persons, bodies Politique, and Corporate within either of the said Vniuersities of Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge or Oxford, or within Westminster, Eaton, or Winchester, or any Cathedrall or Collegiate Church aforesaid, as all other person and persons, bodies Politique and Corporate whatsoeuer ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing any Lands, Tenements, Hereditaments, Proffits, Goods, Chattels, Summes of money, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things mentioned to be giuen, limited, assigned or appointed to or for any of the good and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vses aboue said, That they and euery of them doe well and faithfully imploy the said Lands, Tenements, Hereditaments, Goods, Chattels, Summes of money or other things, according to the true meaning, ordinance, and institution of the Founders, or Giuers of the same, vpon paine of his Maiesties high displeasure, and of such penalties and punishments, as they shall iustly deserue for contemning of his Royall commaundement, in a cause so iust and necessary to be performed, and for their demerits in that behalfe.</p>
            <p>And albeit his Maiestie knoweth, that for and concerning such person and persons, bodies poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique and Corporate as be exempted out of the said Act, such sufficient remedie and reformation by visitations, and other lawfull meanes may be had in the cases aboue said: Yet forasmuch as these proceedings will require time, and draw the parties exempted out of the said Act, from their studies, and exercises of learning, and put them to no small charge; His most excellent Maiestie, hath for their ease and profit taken this more speedy course, by these presents in manner and forme abouesaid; Giuing all and singuler the person and persons, bodies Politique and Corporate abouesaid assured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to know, That whosoeuer shall violate, or not performe his Maiesties Royall commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hereby published, that he, or they, or any of them shall not hope to passe away with impunity, but shall vndergoe such paines, penalties, and punishments, as by the seuerity of the Lawes of this Realme, may be inflicted and imposed vpon so grieuous and vncharitable offendours.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Giuen at his Maiesties Castle of Rockingham <date>the xi. of August 1605. in the third yeere of his Maiesties Reigne of Great Britaine, France and Ireland.</date>
                  </hi>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <closer>God saue the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>❧ Imprinted at London by Robert Barker, Printer to the Kings most Excellent Maiestie. ANNO DOM. 1605.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>